# 你看这跟豌豆黄截然不同是吧
See? This is totally different from the 'Wan Dou Huang' pea cake, right?
# 这要夏天 来这么一块 爽
It's absolutely cool to have such a piece in the hot summer
# 做一个豌豆糕
Let's make a 'Wan Dou Gao' pea cake
# 大爷你看这柿子
Da Ye, look at the dried persimmon
# 这个是没泡之前的
This one is not soaked
# 然后这个是刚才把那洗干净了 泡一下
This one has been washed and soaked for a while
# 今天我一看这柿饼我就爱吃
I already love this snack just because of the dried persimmon
# 你这是去皮豌豆 去皮豌豆用的
-These are uncoated peas. -We are using uncoated peas today
# 面点一般要的去皮的多 洗透亮了
We usually use uncoated peas to make pastries. Wash them until clean and shiny
# 慢慢煮上它 凉水下锅师父
Let's boil it slowly. I'm gonna put the peas into the wok with cold water, master
# 煮多长时间 煮二十分钟
-For how long are you going to boil it? -20 minutes
# 二十分钟要不够就半个小时
If not enough, boil it for half an hour then
# 咱们看自己家的火 放点碱
The time depends on your cooking stove. Add some soda
# 过去老的手法都放点碱
In classic protocols, soda is often used under such situations
# 不放碱还不好吃 大约有四克的碱
-It'll taste bad without soda. -This is about 4 grams of soda
# 有的现在人胃不好 产生胃酸吃豆
Some people may suffer from too much stomach acid after eating peas
# 放了碱就不胃酸了 酸碱中和了
-This problem can be settled by adding soda. -Soda can neutralize acid #这里化学上说是不对的...不过neutralize也可以有抵消的意思
# 第二条就是容易烂
What else, the peas become mushy faster (with soda)
# 它还有那种特殊的香味
Also it gives a special aroma
# 碱特殊的香味跟豆融在一起 非常香
The special aroma of soda fuses well with that of peas and smells awesome
# 在这我跟网友普及一下煮豆的技巧
Here I want to introduce you guys the tricks of boiling beans
# 我们煮豆的时候适当地放点碱 少放水
When boiling beans, you can add a moderate amount of soda, but add less water
# 比如熬一个豆粥 我需要一锅水
For example, you may need a whole pot of water when cooking a bean congee
# 但是我刚开始不要放一锅水
But don't add that much water in the beginning
# 放三分之一锅的水
Just fill one-third of a whole pot
# 一开锅了我就点点儿凉水
When it boils, add some cold water
# 开锅了就点点儿凉水
When it boils again, add some cold water
# 一直点到最后 我需要的水就够了
Repeat this step until the end, and there'll be enough water in the congee
# 这时候的豆经过冷激热煮
In this way, the beans are chilled and boiled repeatedly
# 它迅速的开花儿
They'll 'blossom' (become stewed and soft) very fast
# 所以碱的作用非常好
So the soda plays an important role here
# 这儿泡的是栀子水 栀子
-Here is some gardenia water. -Gardenia
# 过箩 这是为了给它调一下色
Filter it. This is for the color
# 大爷你看到没有 黄黄的水
You see that, Da Ye? The water becomes yellow
# 现在这豌豆已经开锅了 现在变成小火
Now the peas are boiling. Turn it to low heat now
# 一边煮着豆我一边切柿饼 切成丝儿
While boiling the peas, let me cut the dried persimmon into slices
# 咱们把它码上 码成一图案码上一花儿
Let's tile them here. Tile the slices into a pattern
# 它里面一般还放一些果脯 什锦果脯
Generally we use some preserved fruit in this dish. Mixed preserved fruit
# 这个蜜饯果脯
The preserved fruit...
# 在我们做食材的时候用的很广泛
is widely used in all kinds of dishes
# 八宝饭 还有其它一些馅儿心
Such as in 'Ba Bao Fan' (eight-treasure rice pudding), and in some other kinds of stuffings
# 好了 这个待用 这个待会拌在豆里
Ok. This is ready for use. We'll mix it with peas
# 这要过箩么 不过箩大爷
-Are you going to sift it? -No, Da Ye
# 要吃有颗粒状的 这个吃法有劲
-We are going to eat with these granules. -That's interesting
# 这会儿我倒点刚才泡的栀子水
Now I'm adding some gardenia water that we prepared
# 稍微来一点点
Just a little bit
# 豌豆一般 咱只要泡了之后
Generally... If you soak the peas in advance
# 第二天蒸可不爱烂了
They won't become soft if you steam them for a long time on the second day
# 而且就得现加碱现熬
You need to boil it on time with soda
# 稍微的这会儿点一点糖
Now add some sugar
# 这会儿点糖 先放了糖它也不爱烂
Add sugar now. The peas won't turn mushy easily if sugar is added too early
# 先放糖有时候糖一渍 我感觉不爱烂
If sugar is added in the beginning, it'll 'pickle' the peas, which will become tough
# 把果料放进去
Add the fruits now
# 其实这可以放很多不少的料是吧
Actually we can add a lot of stuff here, right?
# 主要是它得有青梅 腌的青梅
Well, the most important ingredient should be ome fruit. Pickled ome fruit
# 没有 没买着
But we don't have it here. We couldn't find it anywhere
# 行了
Done
# 我把这个 桂花酱 糖桂花
Let me add the sweet osmanthus jam. Sugar osmanthus jam
# 抹这一层 增加花香气
Smear it like this to enhance the aroma of flowers
# 而且它那甜口也特别润
Also it is 'nourishly' sweet
# 擓到里边 这豌豆一定不要熬太干
Scoop it inside. The pea paste must not be too dry
# 刮平 你看这跟豌豆黄截然不同
Flatten it. See? This is totally different from 'Wan Dou Huang' pea cake
# 能吃到豆的口感
as you can feel the texture of the peas
# 行了晾凉了下冰箱 歇会儿吧
Ok. When it cools down, put it into the fridge. Let's have a rest
# 定好了
Now it becomes solid
# 这在家里边 炎热的夏天吃上一块
If you have a piece of this at home, in the hot summer
# 尤其那小朋友
Kids will definitely love it
# 好吃 它跟豌豆黄有截然不同的口感
Delicious. It has a totally different texture from 'Wan Dou Huang' pea cake
# 那个是属于细腻
'Wan Dou Huang' has a more silky texture
# 这个虽然是粗
Though this one is rougher
# 但是它有吃豆的那种感觉 沙
-It gives you a feeling of eating peas. -Mushy
# 还有淡淡的桂花的香气
Also with a light fragrance of sweet osmanthus
# 我告诉你这要夏天 来这么一块 爽
I bet it's absolutely cool to have such a piece in the hot summer
# 晚上我把所有的兜
At night, I searched through
# 都掏出来
all my pockets
# 那是同事凑份子啊
That was the wedding gift money from my colleagues
# 最多五毛钱
The largest amount was 0.5 yuan
# 最少两毛钱
The smallest amount, 0.2 yuan
# 一共掏下来147.6毛钱
In total, 147.6 yuan
# 我说这是咱们
I said, 'this is the...'
# 今天开始过日子的家底
'initial funds of our family, which starts from today'
# 是我们今天生活的开始
'It is the beginning of our life'
# 大妈呢就是 我可不管这事
Da Ma was like, 'I won't manage that'
# 全是你管
'This is all your business'
# 从这开始
From that time
# 我就开始管家 治家
I started to take care of my family
# 我要求我们跟双方父母有一种约定
I decided that, we had a promise with both families
# 比如我们有钱多给
For example, we send them more money if we have some extra
# 那时候我们双方家长每月给5块钱
At that time, we sent 5 yuan per month to both of our families
# 我们俩人的工资总额
The total amount of our salaries
# 77块钱
was 77 yuan
# 所以给双方家长拿出10块钱
So it was hard for us
# 应该说我挺有难度的
to give them 10 yuan per month
# 因为我说都有小孩了
But when we had a kid
# 我再没有钱
We couldn't spare more money
# 我只能说有钱多给
So I could only say that, we send them more money if we have extra
# 没钱少给
Otherwise, we send less
# 再没钱我不给
If it's worse, we don't send money to them
# 但是我希望
But I was hoping that
# 你们双方的老人
Our parents...
# 是吧
Right?
# 千万别在这个问题上
I hoped that they didn't...
# 特别纠结
...feel bad about this issue (not sending enough money)
# 我也有难度
Because it was really difficult for me
# 因为我们俩人嘛
Both of us...
# 在家里头都行大
were the first kid in our families
# 我们还要给弟弟妹妹们
So we had to be good role models
# 做出一些榜样
for our younger brothers and sisters
# 所以双方老家
So both of our families
# 还对我们还是很谅解的
were very forgiving on us
# 确实我们有孩子以后
Indeed, after we had a kid
# 我们就不给钱
We stopped giving them money regularly
# 但是我要求
But I insisted that
# 不管回谁的家
No matter which family we visited
# 一定要给老人
We must ...
# 因为那边还有个奶奶吗
Because her grandma was still there
# 一定要给奶奶也好
We must buy something when visiting them...
# 给家里人也好
no matter for her grandma, or for the family
# 哪怕买两块钱的东西
even if we could only afford 2-yuan gifts
# 但是两块钱那时候也是钱
However, 2 yuan worthed a lot back then
# 能买好多东西
You could buy a lot of stuff with 2 yuan
# 你要买苹果
For example, if you buy apples
# 两块钱一斤
Apples were 0.2 yuan/jin (0.4 yuan/kg) at that time #这里我觉得应该是两毛？
# 能买十斤苹果
You could buy 10 jin (5 kg) of apples
# 但是家里人也知道
But our families knew
# 我们过日子也比较不容易
that we were living a hard life
# 能拿回4块钱的东西回来
So we could actually return with 4-yuan stuff
# 什么拿点带鱼
such as some beltfish
# 拿点什么
or ...
# 包子
Steamed buns
# 反正有一些常吃
Anyway, like some common food
# 常用的东西
or things that you would usually use
# 八一年以后
After 1981
# 我就开始到外边去闯了
I started to make a living outside
# 曾经也是因为挣工资少
It was because I couldn't make much money (at my job)
# 因为那阵要涨一级工资
At that time, my salary was about to be promoted by one level
# 当时我跟领导的关系没有处理好
But I wasn't going on well with my leader
# 这一级工资就没给我涨了
So my salary was not promoted
# 那阵一级工资6块钱
One level of promotion was 6 yuan per month
# 应该说对我的打击还是挺大的
It was indeed a heavy blow on me
# 6块钱也是不容易
6 yuan was a lot of money
# 是吧
Right?
# 6块钱相当于一个人的
6 yuan was equivalent to ...
# 一个月的生活费
One man's living expenses for one month
# 我特别的失落
I was extremely frustrated
# 也不想再干什么了
and I didn't want to carry on
# 也闹了一些情绪
I was also in a bad mood
# 但是我有好多好朋友
But I had a lot of good friends
# 是吧
Right?
# 就劝我 说你好好的
They persuaded me to keep calm
# 学好厨艺
and focus on studying cooking
# 等你长了本事了
Such that when I become skillful
# 你到哪都挣钱
I could make money everywhere
# 所以这位老哥哥
So that old pal...
# 对我的启发特别大
He inspired me a lot
# 我就开始重新打鼓另开张
And I decided to get back on the track
# 就认真的学厨艺
To study cooking hard
# 正好在中央党校里边
There happened to be a cooking school
# 办一烹饪学校
held in the Party School of the Central Committee of CPC
# 让我去上课
They recruited me as a teacher #如果我没有理解错的话应该是当老师
# 说一天能给30块钱
with a salary of 30 yuan per day